<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xsl/webtemplate.dtd" [ 
    <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "webtemplate.ent">
   %myents;
]>

<chapter id="design-philosophy">
	<title>Design Philosophy</title>
	<section id="design-introduction">
	  	<title>The Philosophy</title>
		<para>
		Webtemplate has been designed to provide a secure base to start the development of web based applications using 
		<olink targetptr="gloss-php" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHP</olink> and <olink targetptr="gloss-pgsql" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PostgreSQL</olink>.
		 It provides the following functionality
	  	<itemizedlist mark="bullet">
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Application Administration 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					User Administration 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Group Administration 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Security 
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Database Management
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Configuration
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					Event Logging
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					PHP and Smarty Templates for adding  your own functionality to the program.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>
				Unit, Functional and Coding Standards Testing can be carried out using a Continuous Integration Server or at the Command Line 
				by using <olink targetptr="gloss-phing" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHING</olink>.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		</para>
	</section>		
	<section id="design-overall">
	  	<title>Programme Design</title>
		<para>	
		Webtemplate has been developed as a base system to develop Web Based Applications from.  It is completely modular and open.  A blank PHP module and smarty template are 
		provided as templates for your own modules.  The blank PHP module includes all the necessary Classes for verifiny users, logging and security.
		</para>
		<para>
		There are five  main directories thay will need files added to or updated.  They are:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>base</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					This directory and its sub-directories are the only ones directly accesses by Apache.  The <olink targetptr="gloss-php" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHP</olink>  files
          					in this directory provide the user interface to Webtamplate and subsequently your own application.  <filename>blank.php</filename> is provided as
          					a template to create your application.  Each function within the application has its own <olink targetptr="gloss-php" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHP</olink>  file.
					</para>
			        	</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>base/docs</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					This is the main documentation directory.  It contains all the files required to generate the documentation for Webtemplate or your application 
          					using <olink targetptr="gloss-docbook" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">DOCBOOK</olink>.  To document the additional functionality you 
          					have added to Webtaemplate to create your application you need to update <filename>using.xml</filename> and <filename>administration.xml</filename> 
          					in the <filename>en/xml</filename> sub-directory
					</para>
			        	</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>includes</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					The <filename>includes</filename> directory is broken down into a number of sub-directories.  Any new functionality you add to Webtemplate should
          					be saved in a subdirectory named after your application or specific functionality you are adding.  You will need to update <filename>general/parameters.class.php</filename>
          					if you add any new setup  parameters to your application and <filename>users/user.class.php</filename> and <filename>general/preferences.class.php</filename> if you 
          					add any new user preferences to the application.
					</para>
					<para>
					Each Class included  in a file is also in a <emphasis role="bold">NAMESPACE</emphasis> of the format <emphasis role="bold">webtemplate/dirname</emphasis>. 
					It is recommended that when you add your own classes you replace "webtemplate" with the name of your own application in your files
					only.  You will also have to update <filename>autoloader.class.php</filename> to strip that name from the filename it uses to load the class.
					</para>
					<para>
					As new functionality is added to Webtemplate which requires configuration options new code modules will be needed to be added to the  <filename>admin\parameters</filename> directory.
					These modules will be based on the <filename>parametersabstract.class.php</filename>.
					</para>
			        	</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>templates</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					The raw <olink targetptr="gloss-smarty" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">SMARTY</olink> templates are saved in this directory.  It is broken down in to sub-directories for 
          					each language that Webtemplate supports.  Currently this is only English.  Each Language sub-directory is then further broken down into the same 
          					structure as the <filename>includes</filename> directory.   New templates are created from <filename>blank.tpl</filename> while <filename>main.tpl</filename> 
          					can be updated to display application specific information after a user has logged in.
					</para>
					<para>
					As new functionality is added to Webtemplate which requires configuration options new templates will be needed to be added to the  <filename>admin\config</filename> directory.
					</para>
			        	</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>menus</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					As new functionality is added to Webtemplate the <filename>mainmenu.json</filename>, <filename>mainmenu.json</filename> 
					and <filename>parammenu.json</filename>may need to be updated.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>tests</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					Webtemplate uses <olink targetptr="gloss-phpunit" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHPUnit</olink> to carry out Unit testing on the core of the application.  
          					All data verification, database access and data manipulation is carried out in Classes stored in the <filename>includes</filename> directory.  The structure of the 
          					<filename>tests</filename> directory matches that of the <filename>includes</filename> directory.
					</para>
					<para>
					You should add new tests to this directory for any new Classes you create as well as update any existing tests for changes you have made to existing Classes.
					</para>
			        	</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>		
	</section>
	<section id="design-versioning">
	  	<title>Versioning</title>
	  	<para>
	  	It is recommended that you use the Semantic Versioning system described at <ulink url="http://semver.org/"/> and that you follow their guidance regarding Major, Minor and Patch
	  	versioning and application changes.
	  	</para>
	  </section>
</chapter>
