<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xsl/webtemplate.dtd" [ 
    <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "webtemplate.ent">
   %myents;
]>

<chapter id="develop-structure">
	<title>Webtemplate Structure</title>
	<section id="develop-interface">
	  	<title>Base System</title>
		<para>
		This paragraph provides a description of all the base programs, include files and Smarty templates
		provided with Webtemplate.
		</para>
			<section id="develop-interface-cli">
				<title>Command Line Programmes</title>
				<para>
				This paragraph contains a list and description of the command line utilities provided 
				with &progname;.
				</para>
				<variablelist>
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>install.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						The program used by the user to configure Webtemplate.  This is located in the 
          						top directory and is not accessible by the webserver.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>makedocs.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This file is located in the docs directory.  It is used to convert the docbook xml
          						files in to html and pdf files that explain how to use Webtemplate. 
						</para>
						<para>
						File permissions prevent the webserver accessing this file.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>				
			</section>
			<section id="develop-interface-modules">
				<title>Modules</title>
				<para>
				This paragraph contains a description of all the <olink targetptr="gloss-php" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHP</olink> 
				programs acessed via the webserver.  These programs along with the <olink targetptr="develop-interface-includes"  targetdoc="develop">
				Include Files</olink> provide the basic functionality of your application.
				</para>
				<variablelist>
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>about.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						Display information about the application including, copyright details, version numbers for Smarty, PHP,
          						PostgreSQL.  This program can only be accessed by members of the admin group.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>admin.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						Displays links to the application's admin programs such as edituser, editgroup, preferences and parameters.
						This page is only displayed to users who have admin rights.  The actual contents are dependant on the specific 
						rights  that the user has.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
					<term>apiv1.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Is the entry point to the <olink targetptr="gloss-rest" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">RESTful API</olink>.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>blank.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is the template to be used to create new programs for the application.   It contains
          						all the code necessary to set up the localle and verify the user. 
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>editconfig.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used to configure Webtemplate by changing various parameters, accessed from the "Parameters" link 
          						in the  Administration page. The parameters are divided into several categories, accessed via the menu on 
          						the left.   This is only acessable by members of the admin group.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>editgroups.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used to add, delete and modify security groups.  Webtemplate uses group based security.  When groups
          						are added as part of the application it is possible to define than as system groups to prevent editing.  This is only
          						accessible by members of the editgroups and admin groups.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>editsettings.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used to set the default customisation of the Webtemplateinstallation. This is only accessible by 
          						members of the admin group.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>editusers.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used to add, disable and modify users.  This is only accessible by members of the editusers and 
          						admin groups.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>index.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is the main page of the application.  It enables the users to login and displays the applications home 
          						page after the user has ligged in.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>logout.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This logs the user out.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>newpasswd.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used when a user has been forced by the administrator to change their password either when the administrator
          						has reset the users password for them or the password has expired.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
        					<term>page.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used when to display templates stored in the <filename>templates/en/pages</filename> directory.  The format is 
          						<filename>page.php?id=filename.html</filename>.  It verifies the file exists in the template directory before displaying it.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

               			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>resetpasswd.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This allows users to request new passwords.  It is enabled by setting the New Password parameter to true.  When 
          						run it checks users are allowed to request new passwords before providing with the correct form.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>register.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This allows new users to register with Webtemplate  It is enabled by setting the New User parameter to true.  When 
          						run it checks users are allowed to register before providing with the correct form.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>showdocs.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is the interface between Webtemplate and the Applications Documentation.  It uses a mapping sytem 
          						to find the correct documentation.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>userprefs.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This allows the user to customise Webtemplate.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>		
			</section>
			
			
			<section id="develop-interface-includes">
				<title>Include Files</title>
				<para>
				This paragraph contains a description of all the Webtemplate include files.  Where appropriate the filename is preceded with the 
				directory it is located in. 
				</para>
				<variablelist>
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>admin/parameters.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This Class used to access the admin, auth, email and required modules used to set up &progname; configuration.  All modules 
          						must be decendents of the <emphasis>parameterabstract</emphasis> class.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>admin/preferences.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This Class is used to Validate, confirm changes to and Save the applications preferences.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>


					<varlistentry>
					<term>application/application.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This class acts as a host for all other classes in &progname;.  As a result there is no requirement to call any other class directly.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

					<varlistentry>
					<term>application/createdocs.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This class used by <filename>makedocs.php</filename> to create the docbook documentation.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

					<varlistentry>
					<term>application/error.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This class contains the Webtemplate Error Object.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>


					<varlistentry>
					<term>application/errorhandler.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This class contains the Webtemplate Error Handlers which override the builtin PHP handlers.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>application/header.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains HTML Headers which are sent with evey file to increase the security of the application.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>application/session.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the Class for configuring the <olink targetptr="gloss-php" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">PHP</olink>
          						<olink targetptr="gloss-session" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">SESSION</olink> variables.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>application/smartytemplate.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						The Smarty_Template_Class inherits the <olink targetptr="gloss-smarty" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">SMARTY</olink> 
          						Class and is used to automatically configure <olink targetptr="gloss-smarty" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">SMARTY</olink> 
          						for the application.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>application/webtemplatecommon.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module sets up the database access requirements. 
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

					<varlistentry>
					<term>config/configure.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This class is used to read, write and save the configuration parameters.  Currently they are saved as a text file but moving
						them to the database is being concidered.
						</para>
					</listitem>	
					</varlistentry>
					
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>general/help.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the mapping between the applications help Ids and the physical help files.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>general/general.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains Class containing functions used by all the applications programs.  
          						The purpose of functions include checking documentation is available, setting the configuration file 
          						and checking the key parameters are set.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>general/localvalidate.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the Static Local Validation Class.  it contains functions to
          						validate such items as user names, e-mail addresses and URLs.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>general/log.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module is used by the application to create, update and maintain it's logfiles.  
          						The logging is controlled by a number of the application's parameters.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

					<varlistentry>
					<term>general/mail.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This modules acts as the interface beetween Webtemplate and PHPMail.  The module controls whither Webtemplate can 
						send mail or not and how it sends it. i.e. via sendmail or smtp.  It also has a test option where the contents of the mail are 
						spooled to a test file located in the <filename>log</filename> directory
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>general/token.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This module is used to create, manage and delete authentication tokens for Wetemplate.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>groups/editgroupsfunctions.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the Class used by <filename>base/editgroups.php</filename> to display, edit, save and delete security groups.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>groups/editgroups.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the Class used by users with "editgroups" permissions to create, update and delete groups
          						groups.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>groups/editiusersgroups.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the Class used by users with "edituser" permissions to assign or remove users fro specific groups. 
          						groups.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>groups/groupfunctions.trait.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains a trait which common group functions.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>install/database.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the static DataBase Class which is used to create and update the back-end database.  The databse 
          						configuration is held in <emphasis>json</emphasis> files in the <filename class="directory" >configure</filename>
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>install/dependancies.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This module is used to check if the Webtemplate Dependancies are available on the target system
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

					<varlistentry>
					<term>install/dependanciesdata.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This module contains the Webtemplate Dependancy Data in 4 arrays
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>install/filemanager.class.php</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This module contains all the functions to create and update the parameters and preference files as well as file containing the
						database connection credentials.  It also sets the file permissions to secure the application.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>users/edituser.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the Class to Create and update users.  Functions are available to validate
          						user input, identify if details have changed and save the information to the database.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>users/user.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the class that the application uses to access user information inorder to
          						log them in and get the application customisation information.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>users/groups.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the class that the application uses to access user security information.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>users/edituserpref.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module contains the class to allow users to update their personal customisation choices. 
          						It includes functions to validate and save the information to the database.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>


			</section>
			<section id="develop-interface-templates">
				<title>Templates</title>
				<para>
				This paragraph contains a description of all the Webtemplate template files.  Where appropriate
				the filename is preceded with the directory it is located in.  
				</para>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
					<term>layout.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This is the main template.  All other templates inherit this template which contains
						the HTML tags required to render a HTML page.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>blank.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This is a blank template that should be used as the basis of all new application
						templates.  It should be copied and renamed to signify its use.  
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>error.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to display any errors that the application encounters.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>main.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This is the main template.  It is used to display the login screen as well as the applications home page.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>admin/about.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to display information about the application such as software version numbers.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>admin/admin.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to access the administration programs.  It uses group security to limit what the 
						user can see dependant on their permissions.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>admin/config.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This is a multi tab template used to access the applications configuration system.  Tabs include Manditory 
						Configuration Items, Administration policies and user settings.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>admin/filenotfound.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is displayed if the requested Help File is not found on the system.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>admin/helpfilenotfound.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						his template is displayed if the requested Help Item is not found on the system.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>admin/prefs.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to display and set the default customisation options for the application
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
								
					<varlistentry>
					<term>groups/delete.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Thsi template is used to confirm deletion of a group.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>groups/edit.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to edit group information such as name and description prior to the group being 
						created or updated.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>groups/list.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to provide the list of groups for the application including names, decriptions and 
						wither they are system or user groups.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/edit.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to edit user information such as names and e-mail addresses prior to the user being 
						created or updated.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/list.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to provide a list of users which have been returned as the result of a search.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/newpasswd.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used by users to request a new password.  
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/passwdrequest.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to create the e-mail sent to users with the new password they have requested.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/prefs.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to display and edit user preferences such as Customisation Options, User's Real Name 
						and e-mail address.  It will also display the groups a user is a member of.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/register.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used for users to enter information into such as username and realname when they create their 
						account for the application.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/search.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This themplate is used by adminsitraotors to search the user database.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					
				</variablelist>
			</section>
	</section>
	<section id="develop-update">
	  	<title>Files that may require updating</title>
		<para>
		This Paragraph contains a list of files  that may require updating when you 
		develop your own application.
		</para>
			<section is="develop-update-menus">
				<title>Menus</title>
				<para>
				The following menus may need updating as you develop your application.  See the existing menus for their structure.
				</para>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>adminmenu.json</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							This is the admin menus and is used to control the contents of <filename>admin.php</filename>. When adding new admin functionality to your 
							application thie menu is updated to allow access to the module via <filename>admin.php</filename> if the current user is in the correct access 
							group.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>mainmenu.json</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							This is the applications main menu and is shown on every page.  Menu items are displayed to the user depending on if they are logged in and if they
							are members of the admin group.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>parammenu.json</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							&progname; configuration parameters are subdivided into seperate categories.  This menu is used to access the individual subcategories.  It is 
							expected that new application parameters are added to their own subcategory.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
						<term>userprefmenu.json</term>
						<listitem>
							<para>
							&progname; users preferences are split into a number of subpages.  This menu is used to configure the individual pages.  It is expected that
							new application preferences will be added two their own page.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</section>
			<section id="develop-update-modules">
				<title>Modules</title>
				<para>
				The following modules may need updating as you develop your application
				</para>
				
				<variablelist>
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>blank.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This module should be copied and renamed to reflect the function it is to carry out.  It may then 
          						be edited to add the code required for it's functionality.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>				
			</section>
			<section id="develop-update-includes">
				<title>Include Files</title>
				<para>
				The following Include Files may need updating depending on the functionality added 
				to the application.  If you upadate any of these files you should also update the associated 
				Unit Test File in the <filename>tests</filename> directory.
				</para>
				<variablelist>
				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>general/help.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This will require updating to map any application help IDs to the approprate 
          						help file.
   						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>general/localvalidate.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This will require validating if you and any new user inputs that require custom
          						validation
   						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>users/user.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This will require updating to provide access to any new customisation options 
          						added to the application.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>

				   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>users/edituserspref.class.php</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This will need updating to allow the user to choose their own customisation 
          						options.
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>

			</section>
			<section id="develop-updatetemplates">
				<title>Templates</title>
				<para>The following templates may require updating as you develop your application.</para>
				<variablelist>
					<varlistentry>
					<term>blank.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template is used to create all your templates.  It should be copied an renamed 
						to reflect the function it is carrying out.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>main.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This should edited to show the applications home page.  Currently it has one line of text 
						indicating a sucessful login.
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					<varlistentry>
					<term>users/preferences/settings.tpl</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This template will need updating if you add any customisation options to the application
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
					<varlistentry>
					<term>build/phpunit.xml</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This PHPUNIT configuration file will need updated to include any new Test Directories added to the application
						</para>
					</listitem>
					</varlistentry>
					
				</variablelist>
			</section>
	</section>
	<section id="develop-config">
		<title>Configuration Files</title>
		<para>
		Webtemplate uses a number of configuration files to operate.  Some of these files are mainted by the developer of the application whilst others are
		generated by <filename>install.php</filename>.  
		</para>
		<para>
		The majority of these files are located in the <filename>config</filename> directory.
		</para>
		<para> 
		These files are explained in the sections below.
		</para>
		<section id="develop-config-smarty">
			<title>Smarty Template Configuration File</title>
			<para>
			The <olink targetptr="gloss-smarty" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">SMARTY</olink> template configuration file is located in the <filename>config</filename> directory.  
			It is the only configuration file that is maintained by the application developer.  There is one <olink targetptr="gloss-smarty" targetdoc="develop" role="glossterm">SMARTY</olink> 
			template configuration file for each of the language supported by the application.
			</para>
			<para>
			The configuration files follow a specific naming convention to allow the application to choose the correct file.  The file name is in the format 
			"language.conf" (eg en.conf for english and fr.conf for french).  The langauage is identified using the "accept-language" header sent by the 
			user's browser.  The values themselves are defined in <ulink url="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47</ulink>.
			</para>
			<para>
			The contents of the <filename>en.conf</filename> file, excluding the licence block, are shown below:
			</para>
			<programlisting>
	## global variables
	application_name = "Web Database Skeleton"
	application_version = "0.5.0+"
	Author = "Sandy McNeil"
	Language = "en"

	## Session configuration
	sessionname = "webdatabase"
	gc_probabilty = 1
	gc_divisor = 100
	lifetime = 168
			</programlisting>
			<para>
			The "Global Variables" section contain the Application Name, Version and Author.  They should be updated to refelect you application's information.  
			This section also includes the Language that the userr has requested.  This is used to define which set of templates to use, if they exist for that language 
			and which translations to use for the php derived messages.
			</para>
			<para>
			The "Session Configuration" section contains the information the application is to use to manage user sessions.  Apart from the sessionname it is recommended 
			that you do not edit any other variables in this section.  The sessionname variable is used to identify wentemplate cookies and should be edited to reflect the name
			of your application.
			</para>
			<para>
			The "gc_probability" and "gc_divisor" are used to decide if the application is to do garbage collection on the logindata and tokens database tables 
			in order to delete stale entries.  Entries in the loginsata table are deleted if they have not been accessed within the time specified in the lifetime variable.  
			The lifetime variable is in hours and the default value og 168 hors is 7 days.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="develop-config-local">
			<title>Local Config</title>
			<para>
			The file <filename>local.conf</filename> contains the information for connecting the application to the database.  The file is created from information the
			user who is installing the application enters in <filename>config.php</filename>.  <filename>local.conf</filename> is created when the user runs 
			<filename>install.php</filename>.  There should be no need to manually edit this file.
			</para>
			<note>
			<para>
			The files <filename>config.php</filename> and <filename>local,conf</filename> are not stored in a directory that is servable by the webserver.
			</para>
			</note>
			<para>
			Example contents for <filename>local.conf</filename> are shown below:
			</para>
			<programlisting>
	[database]
	phptype  = pgsql
	hostspec = testhost
	database = testdatabase
	username = testuser
	password = testpassword
			</programlisting>
		</section>
		<section id="develop-config-parameters">
			<title>Parameters</title>
			<para>
			The <filename>parameters.json</filename> is created and updated by the user when they run <filename>install.php</filename>.  The file contains
			the key configuration parameters used by the application.  They can be updated by an administror using the web interface.  There should be no 
			need to manually edit this file
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="develop-config-preferences">
			<title>Preferences</title>
			<para>
			The <filename>preferences.json</filename> is created and updated by the user when they run <filename>install.php</filename>.  The file contains
			the user preferences used by the application.  They can be updated by an administror using the web interface.  There is no need to manually edit 
			this file.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="develop-config-tests-">
			<title>Database Configuration File for PHPUNIT</title>
			<para>
			The <filename>database.php</filename> is created and updated by the user when they run <filename>install.php</filename>.   The file is
			located in the <filename>tests/_data</filename> directory and is used by the unit tests to access the database.  There is no need to manually edit 
			this file.
			</para>
			<para>
			An example <filename>database.php</filename> is shown below:
			</para>
			<programlisting>
	&lt;?php
	$testdsn["phptype"] = "pgsql";
	$testdsn["hostspec"]  = "testhost";
	$testdsn["database"] = "testdatabse";
	$testdsn["username"] = "testuser";
	$testdsn["password"] = "testpassword";
?&gt;
			</programlisting>
		</section>
	</section>
</chapter>
