<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xsl/webtemplate.dtd"[
    <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "webtemplate.ent">
   %myents;
]>

<chapter id="about">
	<title>About this Guide</title>
	<section id="Copyright">
	  	<title>Copyright Information</title>
    		<para>This document is copyright (c) 2010-&current-year; by Sandy McNeil who wrote it.</para>

    		<blockquote>
      			<para>
       				Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
       			 	document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation
        				License, Version 1.1 or any later version published by the
        				Free Software Foundation; with no Invariant Sections, no
        				Front-Cover Texts, and with no Back-Cover Texts. A copy of
        				the license is included in the source code or can be found at <ulink url="&url-license;">&url-license;</ulink>.
      			</para>
    		</blockquote>
    		<para>
      			If you have any questions regarding this document, its
      			copyright, or publishing this document in non-electronic form,
     			 please contact the Author. </para>
	</section>
	<section id="Disclaimer">
  		<title>Disclaimer</title>
		<para>THIS SOFTWARE IS PROVIDED BY THE COPYRIGHT HOLDERS AND CONTRIBUTORS "AS IS" AND ANY EXPRESS OR IMPLIED WARRANTIES, INCLUDING, BUT
		NOT LIMITED TO, THE IMPLIED WARRANTIES OF MERCHANTABILITY AND FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE ARE DISCLAIMED. IN NO EVENT SHALL THE
		COPYRIGHT HOLDER OR CONTRIBUTORS BE LIABLE FOR ANY DIRECT, INDIRECT, INCIDENTAL, SPECIAL, EXEMPLARY, OR CONSEQUENTIAL DAMAGES
		(INCLUDING, BUT NOT LIMITED TO, PROCUREMENT OF SUBSTITUTE GOODS OR SERVICES; LOSS OF USE, DATA, OR PROFITS; OR BUSINESS INTERRUPTION)
		HOWEVER CAUSED AND ON ANY THEORY OF LIABILITY, WHETHER IN CONTRACT, STRICT LIABILITY, OR TORT (INCLUDING NEGLIGENCE OR OTHERWISE)
		ARISING IN ANY WAY OUT OF THE USE OF THIS SOFTWARE, EVEN IF ADVISED OF THE POSSIBILITY OF SUCH DAMAGE.</para>
	</section>
	<section id="NewVersions">
  		<title>New Versions</title>
		<para>This is the &current-ver; version of &progname;  Guide. It is so named to match the current version of &progname;. </para>
		<para>
			The latest version of this guide can always be found at <ulink url="&url-doc;">&url-doc;</ulink>.
			However, you should read the version which came with the &progname;  release you are using.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="Credits">
  		<title>Credits</title>
		<para>The people listed below have made enormous contributions to the creation of this Application and Guide</para>
		  <variablelist>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>Sandy McNeil <email>amcneil@iee.org</email></term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>The original designer of Webtemplate which this application is based on. </para>
			        </listitem>
      			</varlistentry>
      			<varlistentry>
      				<term>The Bugzilla Team <ulink url="http://www.bugzilla.org" /></term>
      				<listitem>
      					<para>For supplying me the inspiration to design Webtemplate and this documentaion</para>
      				</listitem>
      			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>

	</section>
</chapter>
