<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter SYSTEM "../../xsl/webtemplate.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "webtemplate.ent">
   %myents;
]>

<chapter id="admin">
	<title>Administering &progname;</title>
	<section id="parameters">
	  	<title>&progname; Configuration</title>
		<para>
		&progname; is configured by changing various parameters, accessed from the "Parameters" link in the 
		Administration page (the Administration page can be found by clicking the "Administration" link in the footer). 
		The parameters are divided into several categories, accessed via the menu on the left. The list below is
		description of the different categories and important parameters within those categories. 
		</para>
		<section id="required">
			<title>Required Settings</title>
			<para>
			The core required parameters for any &progname; installation are set here. These parameters must be set 
			before a new &progname;  installation can be used and  administrators should review this list before deploying 
			a new installation. 
			</para>
			<variablelist>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>URL Base</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>This defines the fully qualified domain name and path to this &progname; instance.</para>
						<para>
						Example, if the path to the home page is 
						<filename>http://www.example.com/&progname;/index.php</filename>.  The <quote>URL Base</quote> 
						should be set to <filename>http://www.example.com/&progname;/</filename>. 
						</para>
			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Maintainer</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>The e-mail address of the person who manages this &progname; installation.</para>
			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Doc Base</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>This defines the path to the &progname; documentation.  It is a path relative to the "URL Base".</para>
          						<para>
          						Example, if the path to this page is <filename>http://www.example.com/&progname;/docs/en/admin.html</filename>
          						 then the <quote>Doc Base</quote> should be set to <filename>docs/en/</filename>.
          						</para>
			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Cookie Domain</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>Defines the domain for &progname; cookies. This is typically left blank.</para>
			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Cookie Path</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						 Defines a path, relative to the web server root, that &progname;
					            cookies will be restricted to. For example, if the 
                					<command>urlbase</command> is set to
					           <filename>http://www.example.com/&progname;/</filename>, the 
                					<command>cookiepath</command> should be set to 
                					<filename>/&progname;/</filename>. Setting it to "/" will allow all sites 
                					served by this web server or virtual host to read &progname; cookies.

          						</para>
			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
	 		</variablelist>
		</section>
		<section id="admin-policy">
			<title>Administrative Policys</title>
			<para>
			This page contains parameters for basic administrative functions.
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Logging Level</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This sets the type of information that the &progname; will log.   A detailed explination of
						each logging level can be found in <olink targetptr="logging" targetdoc="manual" />  The further down the list 
						the more information that is logged.
						</para>
						<para>
						Security violations are logged at every level except for None.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Log Rotate</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This sets the frequency the logs are rotated. the options are Daily, Weekly and Monthly.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Open Links in New Windows</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						When set to <quote>Yes</quote> links to the documentation or other sites are opned 
						in either a new window or tab depending on browser seetings
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Max Records</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Sets the maximum number of records that can be returned in a query.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>
		
		<section id="user-authentication">
			<title>User Authentication</title>
			<para>
			This page contains parameters for authenticating users.
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Create Accounts</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						When set to <quote>Yes</quote> new users can create their own acounts.  However depending on 
						default permissions they may not be able to do anything.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>New Password</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						When set to <quote>Yes</quote> users can request a new password.  
						The password is sent to their registered e-mail address.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Password Strength</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This parameter allows the administrator to set the complexity of the passwords used by the system.  In
						all cases the paswords must be at least 8 characters long and no more than 20.
						</para>
						<para>
						The five options are:
							<orderedlist>
      								<listitem>
      									<para>
      									no_constraints - No complexity required.
      									</para>
      								</listitem>
      							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								letters - Lower and/or uppercase letters only
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
      							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								mixed_letters - Passwords must contain letters only with at least one UPPER and one lower case letter.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
       							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								Letters_numbers - Passwords must contain letters and numbers only.  There must be at least 
      								one UPPER and one lower case letter and a number.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
       							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								letters_numbers_specialchars - Passwords must contain at least one UPPER or one lower 
      								case letter, a number and a special character.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
     				
      						</orderedlist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>User Name Regexp</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This parameter contains the <olink targetptr="gloss-regexp"  targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm" >Regular Expression</olink> used to validate usernames.  The default entry allows 
						user names to between 5 and 12 charachers long made up of upper and lower case letters and numbers.
						The maximum length of a user name is 20 characters.
						</para>
						<warning>
							<para>
							&progname; does not check that the <olink targetptr="gloss-regexp" targetdoc="manual"  role="glossterm">Regular Expression</olink> 
							is valid.  If there is an error with your  <olink targetptr="gloss-regexp" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">Regular Expression</olink>  you may be locked out of &progname; until you
							can manually update the  <olink targetptr="gloss-regexp" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">Regular Expression</olink>  in <filename>parameters.php</filename>.
							</para>
						</warning>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>User Name Regexp Description</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This parameter contains the plain english description of the user name  <olink targetptr="gloss-regexp" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">Regular Expression</olink>
						used by the program.  It is limited to 200 characters.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry id="passwd-aging" >
					<term>Password Aging</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This parameter allows the administrator to set the wither users' password expire or not.  If a password has expired
						the user must change it before proceding.
						</para>
						<para>
						The four options are:
							<orderedlist>
								<listitem>
									<para>
									None - Passwords do not expire.  This is the default option when &progname; is
									installed.
									</para>
								</listitem>
								<listitem>
								<para>
								60 Days - Passwords expire after 60 days.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
								90 Days - Passwords expire after 90 days.
								</para>
							</listitem>
							<listitem>
								<para>
								180 Days - Passwords expire after 180 days.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</orderedlist>
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
				<varlistentry>
					<term id="autocomplete">Save Login Details</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This parameter allows the administrator to set wither the user can save their login details in their
						web browser.  Ther are two options "Enable" and "Disable" which allow or disallow the auto complete
						function of the login form.  Depending on the browser the user can still save their username and password
						in the Password Manager but will need to tell the browser to automatically fill in the username abd password 
						the next time they log in.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
		</section>

		<section id="email-configuration">
			<title>Email Configuration</title>
			<para>
			This page contains parameters for configuring the applications e-mail subsystem.
			</para>
			<variablelist>
				<varlistentry>
					<term>Mail Delivery Method</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This is used to specify how email is sent, or if it is sent at all. There are several options included for different MTAs, 
						along with two additional options that disable email sending. "Test" does not send mail, but instead saves it in 
						logs/mailer.testfile for later review. "None" disables email sending entirely. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>E-mail Address</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>This is the email address that &progname; uses as its <quote>From:</quote> address in
          						any e-mail it sends</para>
			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
      				
				<varlistentry>
					<term>SMTP Server</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This is the SMTP server address, if the "mail_delivery_method" parameter is set to SMTP. Use "localhost" if you 
						have a local MTA running, otherwise use a remote SMTP server. Append ":" and the port number, if a 
						non-default port is needed. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>SMTP Username</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Username to use for SASL authentication to the SMTP server. Leave this parameter empty if your server 
						does not require authentication. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>SMTP Password</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						Psssword to use for SASL authentication to the SMTP server. This parameter will be ignored if the 
						"SMTP Username" parameter is left empty.
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

				<varlistentry>
					<term>SMTP Debug</term>
					<listitem>
						<para>
						This parameter allows you to enable detailed debugging output. Log messages are printed the 
						web server's error log. 
						</para>
					</listitem>
				</varlistentry>

			</variablelist>
		</section>


		
	</section>		
	<section id="preferences">
	  	<title>&progname; Preferences</title>
		<para>This section sets the default customisation of the &progname; installation. </para>
		<para>
		Each custimisation option has an associated checkbox.  If ticked the user can change the custimisation option
		to suite themselves.  If not checked the the option is not available to the user throut the Preferences link.
		</para>
		<variablelist>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Default Theme</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Selects the default Theme used to display the &progname; pages.  This controls which 
					<olink targetptr="gloss-css" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">CSS</olink> stylesheets are used.  
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Zoom Text Areas</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					When set to <quote>On</quote> the size of <quote>TextAreas</quote> on web pages is increased when the
					<quote>TextArea</quote> is selected. The size returns to normal when not selected.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
			<varlistentry>
				<term>Search Results</term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
					Sets the maximum number of records that can be displayed on a single page. Options are 10, 20,30, 40 and 50.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
	</section>
	<section id="users">
	  	<title>&progname; User Management</title>
		<section id="default-user">
			<title>Creating the Default User</title>
			<para>
			When you first run <filename>install.php</filename> to install the program for the first time the default user is
			created.  This user is called <quote>admin</quote> and has the default password <quote>Admin1admin</quote>.
			</para>
			<para>
			The first thing you need to do when you login is change the password for this account.  You will also need to add an 
			e-mail address so that your update can be saved.
			</para>
		</section>
		<section id="managing-users">
			<title>Managing Other Users</title>
			<section id="searching-users">
				<title>Searching for Existing Users</title>
				<para>
				If you have "editusers" privileges, the "Users" link will appear in the Administration page. 
				</para>
				<para>
				The first screen you see allows you to search for users in a number of ways.  You can search on "User Name",
				 "Real Name" or e-mail address.
				</para>
				<para>
				The search returns a list of users matching your criteria. The list contains the login name, real name, 
				email address, date last logged in, date password last changed  and wither the account is disabled or not.
				</para>
				<para>
				User properties can be edited by clicking 	the login name. 
				</para>
			</section>
			<section id="create-users">
				<title>Create New Users</title>
				<section id="self-registration">
					<title>Self Registration</title>
					<para>
					Users can create their own account by clicking the "New Account" link on the login page 
					if this function has been enabled.  See <olink targetptr="user-authentication" targetdoc="manual" />.
					</para>
					<para>
					Accounts created this way may not have access to the main functionality of the &progname;.
					</para>
				</section>
				<section id="admin-registration">
					<title>Accounts Created by Administrators</title>
					<para>
					This is the recommended way for creating new accounts as it allows the administrator to assign the users
					to specific groups depending on their function.
					</para>
					<para>
					Users with "edit users" privilages can create other users.
					</para>
					<procedure>
						<step>
							<para>
							Go to the users search page from the Administration Page.  Then click in the "add a new user link"
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>
							Complete the user name, real name, password and e-mail address fields.  Save the record.
							</para>
						</step>
						<step>
							<para>
							Once the user has been created assign then to the groups required for their role and save the record again
							</para>
						</step>
					</procedure>
				</section>
				<section id="modify-user">
					<title>Modifing User</title>
					<para>
					Once you have found the user you can modify the following fields:
					</para>
					<itemizedlist>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>Real Name</emphasis>:  
							The user's real name
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>Password</emphasis>:  
							The user's password.  If you have enabled the option for users to request new 
							passwords you should not have to do this often.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>Force Password Change</emphasis>: 
							Mark this checkbox when you reset a users password and they will be forced to change 
							it the next time they log in.  This option is only visible when 
							<olink targetptr="passwd-aging">Password Aging</olink> is enabled.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>E-Mail Address</emphasis>:  
							The user's e-mail address
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>Disable Mail</emphasis>: 
							Mark this checkbox to disable all mail functions except new pass word requests for this user
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>Enable User</emphasis>: 
							If this checkbox is checked then the user can login.  If the checkbox is not checked the user will
							not be allowed to login and will be given an <emphasis>	Invalid Username and Password  
							</emphasis>warning.
							</para>
						</listitem>
						<listitem>
							<para><emphasis>Groups</emphasis>: 
							Check the boxes next to the groups this user belongs  to.
							</para>
						</listitem>
					</itemizedlist>
					<para>
					The date that the user was last active is shown at the bottom of the page.
					</para>
				</section>
			
				<section id="delete-accounts">
					<title>Delete User Accounts</title>
					<para>
					User accounts cannot be deleted they can only be disabled.
					</para>
				</section>
			</section>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section id="groups">
	  	<title>&progname; Group Management</title>
		<para>
		Groups allow you control the functionality each user has.  Currently there is no inheritance so 
		users must be added to each group to get access to it's functionality.
		</para>
		<para>
		  Groups are divided into two classes, system and user.  System Groups are created as part of the installation 
		  process and are needed for the correct operation of &progname;.  These groups cannot be edited.  User groups are created 
		  by the administrator and are used to restrict access to individual products.  User groups can be edited and deleted.
		</para>
		<para>
		If you have "editgroups" privileges, the "Groups" link will appear in the Administration page. 
		</para>
		<para>
		The first screen you see gives you a list of groups currently used by &progname;.  
		</para>
		<section id="create_group">
			<title>Create New Group</title>
			<para>
			You can create a new group by carrying out the following steps
			</para>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
					Go to the List Groups Page from the Administration Page.  Then click in the "New Group" link
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
					Complete the Group Name, Group Description, Use for product  and Automatic Group fields.  Save the record
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</section>
		<section id="modify-group">
			<title>Modify Group</title>
			<para>
			Select the group you wish to modify by clicking on it's name on the List Group Page.  
			</para>
			<note>
				<para>
				You cannot edit System Groups.
				</para>
			</note>
			<para>
			Once you have selected the group you can edit the following fields
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>Group Description</emphasis>:  
					The description of the group
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>Use For Product</emphasis>:  
					Wither the group can be used for restricting access to a particular product.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para><emphasis>Automatic Group</emphasis>:  
					When selected all users are automatically members of this group.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</section>
		<section id="delete-group">
			<title>Delete Group</title>
			<para>
			User groups can be deleted when they are no longer required.
			</para>
			<para>
			To delete a group click on the delete link of the desired group on the List Group Page.  
			Confirm the deletion on the next page and the group is deleted.
			</para>
		</section>
	</section>
	
	
	<section id="about-program">
	  	<title>About &progname;</title>
		<para>This contains information on &progname;.  The page contains the following information;</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Version</emphasis>: 
				The current version number of &progname;
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Author</emphasis>: 
				The name of the author who developed &progname;
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>PHP Version</emphasis>: 
				The version of PHP which &progname; is currently running on.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>SMARTY Version</emphasis>: 
				The cersion of the SMARTY Templating Engine currently being used.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Server Name</emphasis>: 
				The fully qualified domain name of the server
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Server Software</emphasis>: 
				The version of Apache and Operating System.
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Server Admin</emphasis>: 
				The e-mail address of the Web Server's administrator
				</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para><emphasis>Database Version</emphasis>: 
				The type and version of databse being used.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
	</section>
</chapter>
