<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<!-- New document created with EditiX at Sat Feb 05 10:54:45 GMT 2011 -->
<!DOCTYPE glossary PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"  "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "webtemplate.ent">
 
   %myents;
]>

<glossary id="glossary">

	<glossdiv>
	    	<title>0-9, high ascii</title>

	    	<glossentry id="gloss-htaccess">
      			<glossterm>.htaccess</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>Apache web server, and other NCSA-compliant web servers,
       					 observe the convention of using files in directories called 
        					<filename>.htaccess</filename>
       					 to restrict access to certain files. They are not currently used in [[progname}}
       				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
 	</glossdiv>

	 <glossdiv id="gloss-a">
		<title>A</title>

	    	<glossentry id="gloss-ant">
      			<glossterm>ANT</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				Apache Ant is a software tool for automating software build processes. It originally 
        				came from the Apache Tomcat project in early 2000. It was a replacement for the unix 
        				make build tool, and was created due to a number of problems with the unix make.
        				It is similar to Make but is implemented using the Java language, requires the Java 
        				platform, and is best suited to building Java projects.
				</para>
				<para>
				The most immediately noticeable difference between Ant and Make is that Ant uses XML 
				to describe the build process and its dependencies, whereas Make uses Makefile format. 
				By default the XML file is named <filename>build.xml</filename>.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		
	</glossdiv>
	
	<glossdiv id="gloss-c">
	    	<title>C</title>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-composer">
	    		<glossterm>Composer</glossterm>
	    		<glossdef>
	    			<para>
	    			Composer is an application-level package manager for the PHP programming language that provides a standard format for 
	    			managing dependencies of PHP software and required libraries.
				</para>
				<para>
				Composer runs through the command line and installs dependencies (e.g. libraries) for an application. It also allows users 
				to install PHP applications that are available on <glossterm linkend="gloss-packagist">Packagist</glossterm> which is its main 
				repository containing available packages. It also 	provides autoload capabilities for libraries that specify autoload information 
				to ease usage of third-party code.
	    			</para>
	    		</glossdef>
	    	</glossentry>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-css">
      			<glossterm>CSS</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				Cascading Style Sheets (CSS) is a style sheet language used to describe the presentation semantics 
        				(the look and formatting) of a document written in a markup language. Its most common application 
        				is to style web pages written in HTML and XHTML, but the language can also be applied to any kind 
        				of XML document, including SVG and XUL.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	</glossdiv>
	
<glossdiv id="gloss-d">
	    	<title>D</title>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-docbook">
      			<glossterm>DocBook</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
				 DocBook is a semantic markup language for technical documentation. It was originally intended for writing technical documents related to computer 
				 hardware and software but it can be used for any other sort of documentation.
				</para>
				<para>	
				As a semantic language, DocBook enables its users to create document content in a presentation-neutral form that captures the logical structure 
				of the content; that content can then be published in a variety of formats, including HTML, XHTML, EPUB, PDF, man pages, Web help and HTML Help, 
				without requiring users to make any changes to the source. In other words, when a document is written in DocBook format it becomes easily portable 
				into other formats. It solves the problem of reformatting by writing it once using XML tags.
				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	</glossdiv>

	  <glossdiv id="gloss-h">
	    	<title>H</title>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-html">
      			<glossterm>HTML</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				HTML, which stands for HyperText Markup Language, is the predominant markup language for 
        				web pages. HTML is the basic building-blocks of webpages.
				</para>
				<para>
				HTML is written in the form of HTML elements consisting of tags, enclosed in angle brackets, 
				within the web page content. HTML tags normally come in pairs. 
				The first tag in a pair is the start tag, the second tag is the end tag (they are also called 
				opening tags and closing tags). In between these tags web designers can add text, tables, 
				images, etc.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	</glossdiv>
	
	  <glossdiv id="gloss-j">
	    	<title>J</title>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-jar">
      			<glossterm>JAR</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
	    			A JAR (Java Archive) is a package file format typically used to aggregate many Java class files and associated metadata and 
	    			resources (text, images, etc.) into one file to distribute application software or libraries on the Java platform.
				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
		
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-javascript">
      			<glossterm>Javascript</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
	    			 JavaScript, also known as ECMAScript is a prototype-based, object-oriented scripting language that 
	    			 is dynamic, weakly typed and has first-class functions. It is also considered a functional programming 
	    			 language like Scheme and OCaml because it has closures and supports higher-order functions.   				
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	</glossdiv>


	  <glossdiv id="gloss-p">
	    	<title>P</title>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-packagist">
	    		<glossterm>Packagist</glossterm>
	    		<glossdef>
	    			<para>
	    			Packagist is the main <glossterm linkend="gloss-composer">Composer</glossterm> repository. It aggregates public PHP 
	    			packages installable with <glossterm linkend="gloss-composer">Composer</glossterm>.
	    			</para>
	    		</glossdef>
	    	</glossentry>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-phar">
      			<glossterm>PHAR</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				The phar extension provides a way to put entire PHP applications into a single file called a "phar" (PHP Archive) for easy distribution and installation. 
        				Phar archives are best characterized as a convenient way to group several files into a single file. As such, a phar archive provides a way to distribute a 
        				complete PHP application in a single file and run it from that file without the need to extract it to disk. Additionally, phar archives can be executed by PHP 
        				as easily as any other file, both on the commandline and from a web server.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	    	<glossentry id="gloss-php">
      			<glossterm>PHP</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>PHP is a widely-used general-purpose scripting language that is especially suited for 
        					Web development and can be embedded into HTML.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	    	<glossentry id="gloss-phpunit">
      			<glossterm>PHP Unit</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				PHPUnit is a unit testing framework for the PHP programming language. PHPUnit was created by Sebastian Bergmann and its development 
        				is hosted on GitHub.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>


	    	<glossentry id="gloss-pgsql">
      			<glossterm>PostgreSQL</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				PostgreSQL, often simply "Postgres", is an object-relational database management system (ORDBMS) with an emphasis on extensibility and 
        				standards-compliance. As a database server, its primary function is to store data, securely and supporting best practices, and retrieve it later, 
        				as requested by other software applications, be it those on the same computer or those running on another computer across a network 
        				(including the Internet). It can handle workloads ranging from small single-machine applications to large Internet-facing applications with many 
        				concurrent users. 
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>

	</glossdiv>
	<glossdiv id="gloss-r">
		<title>R</title>
		<glossentry id="gloss-regexp">
			<glossterm>REGULAR EXPRESSION</glossterm>
			<glossdef>
				<para>
				In computing, a regular expression (abbreviated regex or regexp) is a sequence of characters 
				that forms a search pattern, mainly for use in pattern matching with strings, or string matching, 
				i.e. "find and replace"-like operations. The concept arose in the 1950s, when Kleene formalized 
				the description of a regular language, and came into common use with the Unix text processing 
				utilities ed, an editor, and grep (global regular expression print), a filter.
				</para>
			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
	
	</glossdiv>
	  <glossdiv id="gloss-s">
	    	<title>S</title>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-selenium">
	    		<glossterm>SELENIUM</glossterm>
	    		<glossdef>
	    			<para>
	    			Selenium is a portable software testing framework for web applications. Selenium provides a record/playback tool for authoring 
	    			tests without learning a test scripting language (Selenium IDE). It also provides a test domain-specific language (Selenese) to 
	    			write tests in a number of popular programming languages, including Java, C#, Groovy, Perl, PHP, Python and Ruby. The tests can 
	    			then be run against most modern web browsers. Selenium deploys on Windows, Linux, and Macintosh platforms.
	    			</para>
	    		</glossdef>
	    	</glossentry>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-session">
      			<glossterm>SESSION</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				Session support in PHP consists of a way to preserve certain data across subsequent accesses. This enables you to 
        				build more customized applications and increase the appeal of your web site. 
        				</para>
        				<para>
        				A visitor accessing your web site is assigned a unique id, the so-called session id. This is either stored in a cookie 
        				on the user side or is propagated in the URL.  This allows you to store data between requests.
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
	    	<glossentry id="gloss-smarty">
      			<glossterm>SMARTY</glossterm>

      			<glossdef>
        				<para>
        				Smarty is a template engine for PHP, facilitating the separation of presentation (HTML/CSS) from application logic.  
        				This implies that PHP code is application logic, and is separated from the presentation. 
        				</para>
      			</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
	
	</glossdiv>
	<glossdiv id="gloss-u">
		<title>U</title>
		<glossentry id="gloss-unittest">
		<glossterm>Unittest</glossterm>
		<glossdef>
			<para>
			In computer programming, unit testing is a software testing method by which individual units of source code, sets of one or more computer program modules 
			together with associated control data, usage procedures, and operating procedures, are tested to determine whether they are fit for use.  Intuitively, one can 
			view a unit as the smallest testable part of an application. In procedural programming, a unit could be an entire module, but it is more commonly an individual 
			function or procedure. In object-oriented programming, a unit is often an entire interface, such as a class, but could be an individual method.  Unit tests are 
			short code fragments created by programmers or occasionally by white box testers during the development process. It forms the basis for component testing.
			</para>
		</glossdef>
		</glossentry>
	</glossdiv>
	
	  <glossdiv id="gloss-x">
	  	<title>X</title>
	  	<glossentry id="gloss-xml">
	  	<glossterm>XML</glossterm>
	  	<glossdef>
	  		<para>
	  		Extensible Markup Language (XML) is a markup language that defines a set of rules for encoding documents in a format which is both human-readable 
	  		and machine-readable. It is defined by the W3C's XML 1.0 Specification and by several other related specifications.
	  		</para>
	  	</glossdef>
	  	</glossentry>
	  	
	  	<glossentry id="gloss-xvfb">
	  	<glossterm>XVFB</glossterm>
	  	<glossdef>
	  		<para>
	  		Xvfb or X virtual framebuffer is a display server implementing the X11 display server protocol. In contrast to other display servers 
	  		Xvfb performs all graphical operations in memory without showing any screen output. From the point of view of the client, it acts 
	  		exactly like any other X display server, serving requests and sending events and errors as appropriate. However, no output is shown. 
	  		</para>
	  	</glossdef>
	  	</glossentry>
	  		
	  </glossdiv>

</glossary>

