<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter  SYSTEM "../../xsl/webtemplate.dtd" [
    <!ENTITY % myents SYSTEM "webtemplate.ent">
   %myents;
]>

<chapter id="using">
	<title>Using &progname;</title>
	<section id="using-register">
		<title>Registering</title>
		<warning>
			<para>
			Attempts to register with an existing e-mail address will be logged along with your IP address and the owner notified.
			</para>
		</warning>
		<para>If allowed by the &progname; administrator you can register yourself as a user by clicking on the 
		<emphasis>New Account</emphasis> link on the login page.  If this link is not available you will need to request an
		account from the administrator.
		</para>
		<para>
		Once you click on the new account link you will need to enter a valid email address that belongs to you.  When you submitt
		your request for a new acount using the <emphasis>Request Account</emphasis> button your e-mail address will be validated
		and an email sent to you with a link to complete the registration process.
		</para>
		<para>
		When you click on the link in the email you will be directed to the New Account Form which you will need to complete and submit.   
		You will need the following information to complete the form:
		</para>
		<variablelist>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>User Name</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					This is your chosen username.  The default setting allows user names of between 5 and 12 
          					characters long and can  contain Upper and Lower cases letters and numbers.  This name 
          					must be unique and the system will reject duplicates.
          					</para>
          					<para>
          					The system administrator can change the username format.  If your user name is rejected 
          					please read the error message to obtain the correct format or contact the administrator.
          					</para>
          		        		</listitem>
      			</varlistentry>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>Password</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					Enter your chosen password in this field.  It should be between 8 and 20 characters long and depending on 
          					how &progname; is configured be in one of the following formats:
						<orderedlist>
      							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								no_constraints - No complexity required.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
      							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								letters - Lower and/or uppercase letters only
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
      							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								mixed_letters - Passwords must contain letters only with at least one UPPER and one lower case letter.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
       							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								Letters_numbers - Passwords must contain letters and numbers only.  There must be at least 
      								one UPPER and one lower case letter and a number.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
       							<listitem>
      								<para>
      								letters_numbers_specialchars - Passwords must contain at least one UPPER or one lower 
      								case letter, a number and a special character.
      								</para>
      							</listitem>
     				
      						</orderedlist>
          					
          					</para>
          					<para>
          					You must confirm your password in the <emphasis>Confirm Password</emphasis> box.
          					</para>
          		        		</listitem>
      			</varlistentry>
		   	<varlistentry>
        				<term>Real Name</term>
        				<listitem>
          					<para>
          					Your Real name is entered here.
          					</para>
          		        		</listitem>
      			</varlistentry>
		</variablelist>
		<para>
		If any errors are encountered they are displayed at the top of the form in a red box.  After you correct the error you can
		resubmit your account request.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="using-resetpassword">
		<title>Reset Password</title>
		<para>If allowed by the &progname; administrator you can request a new password by clicking on the 
		<emphasis>Forgot Your Password?</emphasis> link on the login page.   If this link is not available you will 
		need to request a new password from the administrator.
		</para>
		<para>
		To obtain a new password enter your <emphasis>User Name</emphasis> in the box and click on the 
		<emphasis>New Password</emphasis> button.  If your User Name and e-mail address are valid a 
		password reset link will be sent to you.
		</para>
		<para>
		Once you have received the e-mail with the link either click on it or copy it into your browser.  This will 
		open a page that allows you to enter a new password. 
		</para>
  		<para>
          		Your password should be between 8 and 20 characters long and depending on 
          		how &progname; is configured be in one of the following formats:
			<orderedlist>
      				<listitem>
      					<para>
      					no_constraints - No complexity required.
      					</para>
      				</listitem>
      				<listitem>
      					<para>
      					letters - Lower and/or uppercase letters only
      					</para>
      				</listitem>
      				<listitem>
      					<para>
      					mixed_letters - Passwords must contain letters only with at least one UPPER and one lower case letter.
      					</para>
      				</listitem>
       				<listitem>
      					<para>
      					Letters_numbers - Passwords must contain letters and numbers only.  There must be at least 
      					one UPPER and one lower case letter and a number.
      					</para>
      				</listitem>
       				<listitem>
      					<para>
      					letters_numbers_specialchars - Passwords must contain at least one UPPER or one lower 
      					case letter, a number and a special character.
      					</para>
      				</listitem>	
      			</orderedlist>
         		</para>
		
		<para>
		Once the same valid password is entered in both fields click on <emphasis>Change Password</emphasis> button.  
		Once your request has been validated 
		a confirmation page is displayed by clicking on the <emphasis>Continue</emphasis> button you are 
		returned to the login page where you can use your User Name and New Password to login.
		</para>
		<para>
		If any errors are encountered they are displayed at the top of the form in a red box.  The only error you 
		can correct as a user is ensuring thet your username is valid.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="using-login">
		<title>Login</title>
		<para>
		One you have an account and password you can log in.  This is done by entering your <emphasis>Username and Password
		</emphasis> in the boxes provided and clicking on the login button.
		</para>
		<para>
		If any errors are encountered, such as an invalid Username/Password combination, they are displayed at the top of the form 
		in a red box.
		</para>
		<para>
		If password aging has been enabled you will be informed if your password is due to expire as a 14 day countdown.  You can change 
		your password at any time during this 14 days.  Once your password has expired you will need to change it before you can use &progname;
		again.  At this point you are presented with a page to enter your new password.  If you do not wish to change your password at this
		time click on <emphasis>Cancel</emphasis> button and you will be returned to the login page.
		</para>
		<para>
		Once you have sucessfully logged in you can then use &progname;.  The front page also displays the date and time you last used
		&progname; rather than when you last logged in.
		</para>
		<para>
		The functionality you have available depend on the permissions you have been assigned.
		</para>
		<para>
		If the administrator has enabled Password Aging and your password is due to expire within 15 days you will be given a warning at
		the top of the screen along with a link to change your password.  
		</para>
		<para>
		If your password has expired or the administrator has reset it for you and is forcing you to change it at first login you will be redirected 
		to the password change screen.  If this happens you will be unable to continue using &progname; until you have changed your password.
		</para>
		<para>
		The administrator can enable or disable the auto complete function of your web browser for the login forms.  You can still save your username 
		and password in your browser's Password Manager.  To fill in your username and pasword the next time you log in click on the User Name Field 
		and select the correct username.  Both the username and password fields are then completed for you.
		</para>
		<para>
		If you have used the wrong password to attempt to login and are advised that you have used an "Invalid Username and password" you must wait 15 seconds 
		before attempting to login again.  &progname; will reject all login attemps within this time period even if they are correct.
		</para>
	</section>
	<section id="using-preferences">
		<title>Setting Your Preferences</title>
		<para>
		Once you have logged in you can view your user preferences page.  The pages has the following 3 tabs
		</para>
			<section id="using-generalpreferences">
				<title>General Preferences</title>		
				<para>
				The General Preferences allow you to configure the applications look and feel.  The site administrator can
				set default values for each item and can also disable your ability to change them. If this has happened then
				they will not appear on this tab. The standard options are:
				</para>
				<variablelist>
				   	<varlistentry>
        						<term>General Apperance</term>
        						<listitem>
          							<para>
          							This sets the theme that is used to display the web pages. It controls the look and
          							format of each page.  Each Theme is built up from
          							a number of <olink targetptr="gloss-css" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">CSS</olink> files.
		          					</para>
          				        		</listitem>
      					</varlistentry>
				   	<varlistentry>
        						<term>Text Area Zoom</term>
        						<listitem>
          							<para>
          							This option controls wither the <olink targetptr="gloss-html" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">HTML</olink> 
          							textarea changes size when it obtains or losses focus.  For this to work 
          							<olink targetptr="gloss-javascript" targetdoc="manual" role="glossterm">javascript</olink> has to be enabled on your 
          							browser.
		          					</para>
          				        		</listitem>
      					</varlistentry>
				   	<varlistentry>
        						<term>Maximum Number of Results to Display</term>
        						<listitem>
          							<para>
          							This sets the number of search results you wish tp display on a single page.
          							The valid values are 10,20, 30, 40 and 50. 
		          					</para>
          				        		</listitem>
      					</varlistentry>
				</variablelist>
			</section>
			<section id="using-nameandpassword">
				<title>Name and Password</title>
				<para>
				This tab allows you to update your profile.  In order to process the update you will need
				to provide your current password.  You can update the following information:
				</para>
				<variablelist>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Password</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						Enter your chosen password in this field.  It should be between 8 and 20 characters long and depending on 
          						how &progname; is configured be in one of the following formats:
							<orderedlist>
      								<listitem>
      									<para>
      									no_constraints - No complexity required.
      									</para>
      								</listitem>
      								<listitem>
      									<para>
      									letters - Lower and/or uppercase letters only
      									</para>
      								</listitem>
      								<listitem>
      									<para>
      									mixed_letters - Passwords must contain letters only with at least one UPPER and one lower case letter.
      									</para>
      								</listitem>
       								<listitem>
      									<para>
      									Letters_numbers - Passwords must contain letters and numbers only.  There must be at least 
      									one UPPER and one lower case letter and a number.
      									</para>
      								</listitem>
       								<listitem>
      									<para>
      									letters_numbers_specialchars - Passwords must contain at least one UPPER or one lower 
      									case letter, a number and a special character.
      									</para>
      								</listitem>	
      							</orderedlist>
         						</para>
          						<para>
          						You must confirm your password in the <emphasis>Confirm Password</emphasis> box.
          						</para>
          		        			</listitem>
	      			</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Real Name</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						You can change your real name here.
	          					</para>
          			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
			   	<varlistentry>
        					<term>Email Address</term>
        					<listitem>
          						<para>
          						This is used to send you updates such as a new password if requested.
          						</para>
          			        		</listitem>
      				</varlistentry>
			</variablelist>
			</section>
			<section id="using-permissions">
				<title>Permissions</title>
				<para>
				This tab show the groups you are a member off.  Default groups which all users are members of are
				indicated with a <emphasis>(*)</emphasis>
				</para>
			</section>
	</section>
	<section id="using-logout">
		<title>Logout</title>
		<para>
		In order to logout click on the <emphasis>Logout</emphasis> link on either the top or bottom menus.
		</para>
	</section>
	<xi:include  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="app.xml" />
</chapter>
